Rishi Mittal

Engineering Manager @ Careem

+971-554076273 | rimittal44@gmail.com | LinkedIn | Twitter | Github | Dubai, U.A.E

PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

Software Engineer with experience building infrastructure, products and who believes in automation. Extensive experience working in Engineering teams of Health, Food, Ride Hailing, Payment product based Unicorn startups globally.

Experience working in transitioning monolith architecture to microservices based, TDD, SOLID principles, experience in designing complex services and components, understands business strategy, actively seeks new ideas, opportunities, methods, trends and actively encourages team to adopt these practices.

TECH STACK

Back End	Python, PHP, Django, Flask, Lumen, Java, Microservices, APIs, Site Reliability Engineering, DevOps
Infrastructure	AWS, Jenkins, Docker, OpenStack
Data Stores	MySQL, ElasticSearch, MongoDB, Memcached, Cassandra, Redis, Apache Solr
Web Servers	Apache Tomcat, Apache HTTP Server, Nginx

EXPERIENCE

Careem | Dubai, United Arab Emirates

Careem. Inc, is the MENA region's leading consumer platform, offering products in Ride hailing, food-delivery, deliveryAnything, payments etc. It is delivering +1M food deliveries every month, and more than +8M rides every day. Careem is now part of Uber as a result of a \$3.1B deal.

Engineering Manager

Jan2020 - Present

- Leading Squad of 10 Backend Engineers, responsible for career growth, coaching, 1:1s, and professional growth for 5 Backend Engineers.
- Responsible for Shops & OrderAnything Business Verticals and all the engineering deliveries.
- Project Management focussed Agile Practices.
- Scaled platform through orders in early 2k to over 40k orders per day
- Drove redesign of the consumer-facing app through two iterations improving app-open bounces.
- System & Schema design, features of Merchant & Catalogue Service.
- Driving re architecture of services like search, product catalog.

- Features & deployment pipelines for Search & Discovery Service, that indexes all the merchant info & catalogues to ElasticSearch, and api's for listing merchants, sections, collections, search based on tags, cuisines, dishes etc.
- Plan, build, bootstrap Promotions & Offer Service, to create/redeem promotions(user/merchant/bank/city), apis for integrating with loyalty Service, automation of promotions based on order cancellation, marketing campaigns etc.
- Design and implementation of the framework to measure service reliability, SLI, error budgets per service, SLAs.
- Scalable Gitlab Setup(master-slave/runners) using cloudformation, with monitoring & alerting, adopted by more than 10 services., Defining modules, contracts to consume for CI/CD adoption.
- Scalable laaS for multiple microservices across 4 different environments, CI/CD setup(Gitlab), cloudformation (troposphere/python) & deployments/backups automation in very strict deadlines from scratch.
- Proactive monitoring, On call support, RCA/IM Reports.
- Technologies: Lumen, PHP, Python, ElasticSearch, MySQL, Mongo, Nginx, Supervisor, uWSGI, Cloudformation, AWS

Zomato | Gurgaon, India

Zomato, is a leading food delivery & restaurant discovery company based in India, operating in 23 countries, estimated food deliveries stands at +1M orders per day, and more than +\$1.5B in GMV, +180K delivery fleet.

Engineering Lead Jan2018 – Nov2018

- Design, build & Maintain Infrastructure for Zomato to support (1M Requests/min) and over +1M transactions/day.
- Managing terabytes of data sources(Mysql, Cassandra, Solr/Search, Redis, Cache) Infrastructure.
- Customised Stateless servers to run on Spot Instances(Reducing 80% Server cost), partnered with SpotInst.
- Leading team of 6 high performing engineers, with varied background, skills and expertise & experience.
- Upholding high standards for hiring, managing expectations with stakeholders, regular code reviews within the team, maintaining a healthy work life balance while delivering on company's expectations.
- Regular 1:1s, managing agile ceremonies, incident management and proactive decision making to automate infrastructure scalability.

Senior Software Engineer

July2016 – Jan2018

- Design, plan & implementation of Zomato CodeBase Migration(Php5.5 -> Php7.0), involving automation of server provisioning .
- Modular Libraries/Drivers to connect with backend data sources, adding more scalability and consistent connections.
- Implementation of Graylog stack, improving Observability across multiple services, real-time dashboards to understand the behaviour of core transaction flows and catch outliers.
- Introducing & Setup of Envoy based Service Mesh(ECS platform), & migration of key services to service mesh.
- Improving deployment pipelines, using Ansible, Hipchat(ChatOps) implementation, later on Jenkins. Managing Infrastructure based on AWS(Production & Staging), In-House(OpenStack), responsible for uptime and availability of services.
- Experience around tools like hashicorp Consul, travis, goCD, twemproxy, OpenVPN, mysql-proxy integration,
 SpotInst, sentry, newrelic, jenkins, hipchat deployment integration, percona-toolkit, pagerduty, apache, redis,
 Memcached, Envoy, rotor, gh-ost etc.
- Planning & Migration of Zomato AWS Infrastructure to popular IAAC(terraform), introducing modular approach to provision infrastructure in multiple environments, improving developer productivity.
- Responsible for planning and execution of migrations related to databases, key-value stores, coordination with multiple technology verticals to implement solutions without impacting our customers and merchants.
- Managing 100s of scheduled jobs, workers on production allowing them scale, implementation of solutions like Mesos/Chronos etc.
- Technologies: AWS, Apache, Solr, Python, Flask, Django, MySQL, Haproxy, Nginx, SRE

Practo Technologies | Bangalore, India

Practo Technologies, is leading Health Tech based out of India, operating in 5 countries, provides consumer products (Doctor, Clinic discovery, appointment booking etc.), and B2B products like Practo Ray.

Software Development Engineer

June2015 - July2016

- Design & development of *Practo Hawk (Flask, Python, Mongodb)*, a tool to monitor the business KPIs (appointments, patients added EMR records etc)
- Architecture and development from scratch of *Practo Deplex (Flask, Python, boto API, Fabric tasks, AWS)*, One click deployment tool, Enabling 40+ deployments/day for more than 50 applications.
- Development of *modules in Practo Eden (Java, kafka, Multithreading)*, API based sharded Database layer which uses custom indexing & asynchronous calls.
- Re architecture of *Practo Accounts (In house Single Sign-on Service written in Flask, Python)*, multiple fixes, bugs and enhancements towards OOPS principles.
- Member of the Platform team, started to work with the Infrastructure team, learning devOps practices, CI/CD, cost optimization of AWS Infrastructure, implementation of security practices.
- Technologies: Python, Flask, Django, MySQL, Mongo, Nginx , uWSGI , AWS

C-DAC | Hyderabad, India

C-DAC established its Hyderabad Centre in the year 1999 to work in Research, Development and Training activities embracing the latest Hardware & Software Technologies.

Project Engineer Feb2012 – June2013

- Design & development of *Mentor*, a Content Management Product (Java, Struts2, Spring, Hibernate) deployed at research Institutions in India.
- Research & POC on cross-platform mobile development tools like mosync, phonegap.
- Implementation of Eucalyptus Cloud (Private cloud setup).
- Case Study: Leveraging mobile technology for developing tools for Visually Challenged Kids.
- Technologies: Java, Sprint, Hibernate, Mysgl

OTHER EXPERIENCES

Software Engineer Intern Tech Mentro India	May2010 - July2010
Technical Mentor InterviewBit India (Remote)	Jan2019 - present

EDUCATION

M.Tech (Comp Sc. <i>CGPA: 7.5</i>) IIIT Hyderabad, India	July2013 - May2015
PG-Diploma(Grade: A) C-DAC Hyderabad, India	Sept2011 – Jan2011
B.Tech (Comp Sc, CGPA: 7.0) Rajasthan University Alwar, India	July2007 – July2011

ADDITIONAL PROJECTS

- Index Wiki(Search engine)
- LightWeight -DB Engine
- Internet Of Things(platform to create apps)
- Conversation Analysis over Twitter Data(Intelligent chatter)
- Extracting Yelp Contact data(data extraction & crawling)
- Multithreaded File Server(Distributed File System)